<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tools | Matt Aimonetti]]></title>
  <link href="https://matt.aimonetti.net/articles/categories/tools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://matt.aimonetti.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-04T18:49:19-07:00</updated>
  <id>https://matt.aimonetti.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Aimonetti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Practical guide to StatsD/Graphite monitoring]]></title>
    <link href="https://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2013/06/26/practical-guide-to-graphite-monitoring/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-26T10:26:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2013/06/26/practical-guide-to-graphite-monitoring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Engineers love to improve things. Refactoring and optimizations
drive us. There is just a slight problem: we often do that in a vacuum.</p>

<p>Before optimizing, we need to <strong>measure</strong>.</p>

<p>Without a solid baseline, how can you say that the time you invested in making things better wasn't a total waste?</p>

<p>True refactoring is done with a solid test suite in place. Developers know that their code behavior didn't change while they cleaned things up. Performance optimization is the same thing: we need a good set of metrics before changing anything.</p>

<p>There are plenty of monitoring tools out there, each with its own pros
and cons. The point of this article isn't to argue about which one <strong>you</strong> should use,
but instead to give you the some practical knowledge about <a href="http://graphite.readthedocs.org/en/latest/overview.html">Graphite</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite_fullscreen_800.png" alt="Screenshot of the Graphite UI" /></p>

<p>Graphite is used to store and render time-series data. In other words,
you collect metrics and Graphite allows you to create pretty graphs easily.</p>

<p>During my time at LivingSocial, I relied on Graphite to
understand trends, issues and optimize performance. As my coworkers
and I were discussing my recently announced departure, I asked them how I
could help them during the transition period. Someone mentioned creating a
Graphite cheatsheet. The cheatsheet turned into something much bigger than I expected
and LivingSocial was nice enough to let me publicly publish this
short guide.</p>

<p><em>For a more in depth dive into the statsd/graphite features, look at
<a href="http://blog.pkhamre.com/2012/07/24/understanding-statsd-and-graphite/">this blog post</a></em></p>

<h2>Organizing metrics</h2>

<p>There are <a href="http://graphite.readthedocs.org/en/latest/tools.html">many ways</a> to feed Graphite,
I personally used <a href="https://github.com/etsy/statsd/">Etsy's statsd</a> (node.js daemon) which was being fed
via the <a href="https://github.com/reinh/statsd">statsd RubyGem</a>.
The gem allows developers to push recorded metrics to a statsd server
via UDP. Using UDP instead of TCP makes the metrics collection operation
non blocking which means that while you might theoretically lose a few samples, your
instrumented code performance shouldn't be affected. (Read <a href="http://codeascraft.com/2011/02/15/measure-anything-measure-everything/">Etsy's
blog post</a> to know more about
why they chose UDP).</p>

<p><strong> Tip </strong>: Doing DNS resolution on each call can be a bit expensive (a
few ms), target your statsd server using its ip or use Ruby's <a href="http://www.ruby-doc.org/stdlib-2.0/libdoc/resolv/rdoc/Resolv/DNS.html#method-i-getaddress">resolv</a>
standard library to only do the lookup once at initialization.</p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: <em>I'm skipping the config settings about storage retention, resolution etc.. see the
<a href="http://graphite.readthedocs.org/en/latest/overview.html">manual</a> for more info.</em></p>

<h3>Namespacing</h3>

<p>Always namespace your collected data, even if you only have one app for
now. If your app does two things at the same time like serving HTML and
providing an API, you might want to create two clients which you would namespace
differently.</p>

<h3>Naming metrics</h3>

<p>Properly naming your metrics is critical to avoid conflicts,
confusing data and potentially wrong interpretation later on.
I like to organize metrics using the following schema:</p>

<p><code>
 &lt;namespace&gt;.&lt;instrumented section&gt;.&lt;target (noun)&gt;.&lt;action (past tense verb)&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Example:</p>

<p><code>
accounts.authentication.password.attempted
accounts.authentication.password.succeeded
accounts.authentication.password.failed
</code></p>

<p>I use nouns to define the target and past tense verbs to define
the action. This becomes a useful convention when you need to nest
metrics. In the above example, let's say I want to monitor the reasons for
the failed password authentications. Here is how I would organize the
extra stats:</p>

<p><code>
accounts.authentication.password.failure.no_email_found
accounts.authentication.password.failure.password_check_failed
accounts.authentication.password.failure.password_reset_required
</code></p>

<p>As you can see, I used <code>failure</code> instead of <code>failed</code> in the stat name.
The main reason is to avoid conflicting data. <code>failed</code> is an action and
already has a data series allocated, if I were to add nested data using
<code>failed</code>, the data would be collected but the result would be confusing.
The other reason is because when we will graph the data, we will often
want to use a wildcard <code>*</code> to collect all nested data in a series.</p>

<p>Graphite wild card usage example on counters:</p>

<p><code>
accounts.authentication.password.failure.*
</code></p>

<p>This should give us the same value as <code>accounts.authentication.password.failed</code>,
 so really, we should just collect the more detailed version and get rid
of <code>accounts.authentication.password.failed</code>.</p>

<p>Following this naming convention should really help your data stay clean and
easy to manage.</p>

<h2>Counters and metrics</h2>

<p>StatsD lets you record different types of metrics <a href="https://github.com/etsy/statsd/blob/master/docs/metric_types.md">as illustrated here</a>.</p>

<p>This article will focus on the 2 main types:</p>

<ul>
<li>counters</li>
<li>timers</li>
</ul>


<p>Use counters for metrics when you don't care about how long the code
your are instrumenting takes to run. Usually counters are used for data
that have more of a direct business value. Examples include sales,
authentication, signups, etc.</p>

<p>Timers are more powerful because they can be used to analyze the time
spent in a piece of code but also be used as a counters. Most of my work
involves timers because I want to detect system anomalies including performance
changes and trends in the way code is being used.</p>

<p>I usually use timers in a nested manner, starting when a request
comes into the system, through each of the various
datastores, and ending with the response.</p>

<h2>Monitoring response time</h2>

<p>It's a well known fact that the response time of your application will
both affect the user's emotional experience and their likelihood of completing a transactin.
However understanding where time is being spent within a request is
hard, especially when the problems aren't obvious. Tools like
<a href="http://newrelic.com/">NewRelic</a> will often get you a good overview of
how your system behave but they also lack the granularity you might
need. For instance NewRelic aggregates and averageses the data client side
before sending it to their servers. While this is fine in a lot of cases,
if you care about more than averages and want more detailed metrics, you probably need
to run your own solution such as statsd + graphite.</p>

<p>I build most of my web-based APIs on <a href="https://github.com/mattetti/wd-sinatra">wd_sinatra</a> which
has a <code>pre_dispatch_hook</code> method which method is executed before a
request is dispatched.</p>

<p>I use this hook to both set the "Stats context" in the current thread and extract the client name based on HTTP headers.
If you don't use WD, I'll show how to do the same thing in a
Rack middleware.</p>

<p><code>ruby
def pre_dispatch_hook
  api_client = extract_api_client_name(env)
  Thread.current[:stats_context] = "#{api_client}.http.#{env['wd.service'].verb}.#{env['wd.service'].url}".gsub('/', '.')
  # [...]
end
</code></p>

<p>Then using Sinatra's global before/after filters, we set a unique
request id and start a timer that we stop and report in the after filter. If we were using Rails we'd get the unique identifier generated automatically.</p>

<p>Before filter:</p>

<p>```ruby
require 'securerandom'</p>

<p>before do
  Thread.current[:request_id] = request.env['HTTP_X_REQUEST_ID'] || SecureRandom.hex(16)
  response['X-Request-Id'] = Thread.current[:request_id]
  @instrumentation_start = Time.now
end
```</p>

<p>After filter:</p>

<p><code>ruby
after do
  stat = (Thread.current[:stats_context] || "http.skipped.#{env["REQUEST_METHOD"]}.#{request.path_info}") + ".response_time"
  $statsd.timing(stat, ((Time.now - @instrumentation_start) * 1000).round, 1) if @instrumentation_start
end
</code></p>

<p>Note that this could, and probably <strong>should</strong>, be done in a Rack middleware like this (untested, YMMV):</p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<h1>require whatever is needed and set statsd</h1>

<p>class Stats
  class Middleware</p>

<pre><code>def initialize(app)
  @app = app
end

def call(env)
  request = Rack::Request.new(env)
  Thread.current[:request_id] = request.env['HTTP_X_REQUEST_ID'] || SecureRandom.hex(16)
  response['X-Request-Id'] = Thread.current[:request_id]
  api_client = extract_api_client_name(env)
  Thread.current[:stats_context] = "#{api_client}.http.#{request.request_method}.#{request.path_info}".gsub('/', '.')
  @instrumentation_start = Time.now

  response = @app.call(env)

  stat = (Thread.current[:stats_context] || "http.skipped.#{env["REQUEST_METHOD"]}.#{request.path_info}") + ".response_time"
  $statsd.timing(stat, ((Time.now - @instrumentation_start) * 1000).round, 1) if @instrumentation_start
  response
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Note that the stats are organized slightly differently and will read
like that:</p>

<p><code>
&lt;namespace&gt;.&lt;client name&gt;.http.&lt;http verb&gt;.&lt;path&gt;.&lt;segments&gt;.response_time
</code></p>

<p>The dots in the stats name will be used to create subfolders in graphite.
By using such a segmented stats name, we will be able to use <code>*</code>
wildcards to analyze how an old version of an API compares against a
newer one, which clients still talk to the old APIs, compare response
times, etc.</p>

<h2>Monitor time spent within a response</h2>

<p>We're collecting stats on every request so
we can see request counts and median average response times.
But wouldn't be better if we could measure the time spent in specific
parts of our code base and compare that to the overall time spent in the
request?</p>

<p>We could, for instance, compare the time spent in the DB vs Redis
vs Memcached vs the framework. And what's nice is that we could do that
per API endpoint and per API client. In a simpler case, you might decide to monitor mobile vs desktop. The principle is the same.</p>

<p>Let's hook into ActiveRecord's query generation to track the time spent
in AR within each request:</p>

<p>```ruby
module MysqlStats
  module Instrumentation</p>

<pre><code>SQL_INSERT_DELETE_PARSER_REGEXP = /^(\w+)\s(\w+)\s\W*(\w+)/
SQL_SELECT_REGEXP = /select .*? FROM \W*(\w+)/i
SQL_UPDATE_REGEXP = /update \W*(\w+)/i

# Returns the table and query type
def self.extract_from_sql_inserts_deletes(query)
  query =~ SQL_INSERT_DELETE_PARSER_REGEXP
  [$3, $1]
end

def self.extract_sql_selects(query)
  query =~ SQL_SELECT_REGEXP
  [$1, 'SELECT']
end

def self.guess_sql_content(query)
  if query =~ SQL_UPDATE_REGEXP 
    [$1, 'UPDATE']
  elsif query =~ SQL_SELECT_REGEXP
    extract_sql_selects(query)
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>ActiveSupport::Notifications.subscribe "sql.active_record" do |name, start, finish, id, payload|
  if payload[:name] == "SQL"</p>

<pre><code>table, action = MysqlStats::Instrumentation.extract_from_sql_inserts_deletes(payload[:sql])
</code></pre>

<p>  elsif payload[:name] =~ /.* Load$/</p>

<pre><code>table, action = MysqlStats::Instrumentation.extract_sql_selects(payload[:sql])
</code></pre>

<p>  elsif !payload[:name]</p>

<pre><code>table, action = MysqlStats::Instrumentation.guess_sql_content(payload[:sql])
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  if table</p>

<pre><code>$statsd.timing("#{Thread.current[:stats_context] || 'wild'}.sql.#{table}.#{action}.query_time",
                    (finish - start) * 1000, 1)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>This code might not be pretty but it works (<em>or should work</em>).
We subscribe to <code>ActiveSupport::Notifications</code> for <code>sql.active_record</code>
and we extract the info we need. Then we use the stats context set in
the thread and report the stats by appending
<code>.sql.#{table}.#{action}.query_time</code></p>

<p>The final stats entry could look like this:
<code>auth_api.ios.http.post.v1.accounts.sql.users.SELECT.query_time</code></p>

<ul>
<li><strong>auth_api</strong>: the name of the monitored app</li>
<li><strong>ios</strong>: the client name</li>
<li><strong>http</strong>: the protocol used (you might want to monitor thrift, spdy etc..</li>
<li><strong>post</strong>: HTTP verb</li>
<li><strong>v1.accounts</strong>: the converted uri: /v1/accounts</li>
<li><strong>sql</strong>: the key for the SQL metrics</li>
<li><strong>users</strong>: the table being queried</li>
<li><strong>SELECT</strong>: the SQL query type</li>
<li><strong>query_time</strong>: the kind of data being collected.</li>
</ul>


<p>As you can see, we are getting granular data. Depending on how you setup
statsd/graphite, you could have access to the following timer data for
each stat (and more):</p>

<ul>
<li>count</li>
<li>lower</li>
<li>mean</li>
<li>mean_5</li>
<li>mean_10</li>
<li>mean_90</li>
<li>mean_95</li>
<li>median</li>
<li>sum</li>
<li>upper</li>
<li>upper_5</li>
<li>upper_10</li>
<li>upper_90</li>
<li>upper_95</li>
</ul>


<p>Instrumenting Redis is easy too:</p>

<p>```ruby
::Redis::Client.class_eval do</p>

<p>  # Support older versions of Redis::Client that used the method
  # +raw_call_command+.
  call_method = ::Redis::Client.new.respond_to?(:call) ? :call : :raw_call_command</p>

<p>  def call_with_stats_trace(*args, &amp;blk)</p>

<pre><code>method_name = args[0].is_a?(Array) ? args[0][0] : args[0]
start = Time.now
begin
  call_without_stats_trace(*args, &amp;blk)
ensure
  if Thread.current[:stats_context]
    $statsd.timing("#{Thread.current[:stats_context]}.redis.#{method_name.to_s.upcase}.query_time", 
                     ((Time.now - start) * 1000).round, 1) rescue nil
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  alias_method :call_without_stats_trace, call_method
  alias_method call_method, :call_with_stats_trace</p>

<p>end if defined?(::Redis::Client)
```</p>

<p>Using Ruby's alias method chain, we inject
our instrumentation into the Redis client so we can track the time spent
there.</p>

<p>Applying the same approach, we can instrument the Ruby <strong>memcached</strong> gem:</p>

<p>```ruby
::Memcached.class_eval do</p>

<p>  def get_with_stats_trace(keys, marshal=true)</p>

<pre><code>start = Time.now
begin
  get_without_stats_trace(keys, marshal)
ensure
  if Thread.current[:stats_context]
    type = keys.is_a?(Array) ? "multi_get" : "get"
    $statsd.timing("#{Thread.current[:stats_context]}.memcached.#{type}.query_time", 
                     ((Time.now - start) * 1000).round, 1) rescue nil
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  alias_method :get_without_stats_trace, :get
  alias_method :get, :get_with_stats_trace</p>

<p>end if defined?(::Memcached)
```</p>

<h2>Dashboards</h2>

<p>We now have collected and organized our stats. Let's talk about how to
use Graphite to display all this data in a valuable way.</p>

<p>When looking at timer data series, the first thing we want to do is create an overall represention. Your first inclination is probably an <em>average</em>.</p>

<p>The problem with the mean is that it's the sum of all data
points divided by the number of data points. It can thus be significantly affected by a small number of outliers.</p>

<p>The median value is the number found in the center of the sorted list of
collected data points. The problem in this case is that based on your
data set, the median value might not well represent the real overall
experience.</p>

<p>Neither <strong>median</strong> nor <strong>mean</strong> can summarize the whole story of your system's behavior.
Instead I prefer to use a <strong>5-95 span</strong> (thanks <a href="http://steveakers.com/">Steve
Akers</a> for showing me this metric and most of what I
know about Graphite).
A 5-95 span means that we cut off the extreme outliers above 95% and below 5%.</p>

<h3>Span</h3>

<p>Here is a comparison showing how the graphs can be different for the same
data based on what metric you use:</p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite/graphite-median_vs_mean_vs_span.png" alt="Graphite comparing median vs mean vs span" /></p>

<p>Of course the span graph looks much worse than the other two, but it's
also more representative of the real user experience and thus more
valuable. Here is how you would write the graphite function to get this data.</p>

<p>Given that we are tracking the following data-series:</p>

<p><code>
stats.timers.accounts.ios.http.post.authenticate.response_time
</code></p>

<p>The function would be:</p>

<p>```
diffSeries(stats.timers.accounts.ios.http.post.authenticate.response_time.upper_95,</p>

<pre><code>       stats.timers.accounts.ios.http.post.authenticate.response_time.upper_5)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<h3>Alias</h3>

<p>If you try that function, the graph legend will show the entire
function, which really doesn't look great. To simplify things, you can use an
alias like I did in the graph above:</p>

<p>```
alias(diffSeries(stats.timers.accounts.ios.http.post.authenticate.response_time.upper_95,</p>

<pre><code>             stats.timers.accounts.ios.http.post.authenticate.response_time.upper_5),
  "iOS authentication response time (span)")
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Aliases are very useful, especially when you share your dashboards with
others.</p>

<h3>Threshold</h3>

<p>Another neat feature you might add to your graph is a <strong>threshold</strong>.
A threshold is a visual representation of expectations. Say, for example, that your web service shouldn't be slower than 60ms server side. Let's add a threshold for that:</p>

<p><code>
alias(threshold(60), "60ms threshold")
</code></p>

<p>and here's how it would look in a graph:</p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite/graphite-median_vs_mean_vs_span-with-threshold.png" alt="Graphite with a threshold" /></p>

<h3>Draw Null as Zero</h3>

<p>Another useful trick is to change the render options of a
graph to draw null values as zero.
Open the graph panel, click on <code>Render Options</code>, then <code>Line Mode</code> and check
the <code>Draw Null as Zero</code> box.</p>

<p>Here is a graph tracking a webservice that isn't getting a lot of
traffic:</p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite/nulls_not_drawn_as_zero.png" alt="graphite example" /></p>

<p>You can see that the line is discontinued, that's because the API
doesn't constantly receive traffic. If your data series gets only very
few entries, you might not even see a line. This is why you want to
enable the <code>Draw Null as Zero</code>.</p>

<h3>SumSeries &amp; Summarize or how to get RPMs</h3>

<p>By default graphite shows data at a 10 second interval. But often
you want to see less granular data, like the quantity of requests
per second.</p>

<p>Let's say we didn't use a counter for the amount of requests, but
because we used the middleware I described earlier, we are timing all
responses. Graphite keeps a count of the timers we used, so we can use
this count value with a wildcard:</p>

<p><code>
stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.authenticate.response_time.count
</code></p>

<p>If we were to render a graph for this stat we would see a graph per
client. Right now we only care about showing the total amount of requests.
To do that, we'll use the <code>sumSeries</code> function:</p>

<p><code>
sumSeries(stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.authenticate.response_time.count)
</code></p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite/graphite-not-summarized.png" alt="RPMs not summarized" /></p>

<p>The graph looks pretty but it's hard to understand what kind of request
volume we are getting. We can summarize this data to show 1 min
summaries instead:</p>

<p><code>
summarize(sumSeries(stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.authenticate.response_time.count), "1min")
</code></p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite/graphite-summarize.png" alt="RPMs summarize" /></p>

<p>We can now see the quantity of requests per minute. You could do the same to resolve by hour, day, etc.</p>

<h3>Timeshift</h3>

<p>Graphite has the ability to compare a given metric across two different time spans. For instance, let's compare
today's quantity of logins vs those from last weeks.</p>

<p>To generate today's graph:</p>

<p><code>
alias(summarize(sumSeries(stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.authenticate.response_time.count),"1min"), "today")
</code></p>

<p>Then we use the <code>timeShift</code> function to get last week's data:</p>

<p><code>
alias(timeShift(summarize(sumSeries(stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.authenticate.response_time.count), "1min"),"1w"), "last week")
</code></p>

<p>Graphing both series in the same graph will give us that:</p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite/graphite-timeshift.png" alt="graphite timeshift example" /></p>

<p>Wow, it looks like last week we had an authentication peek for a few
hours. Why? It would be interesting to graph our promos and sales in the same
graph to see if we can find any correlations.</p>

<p>Depending on your domain, you might want to compare against different
time slices. Just change the second <code>timeShift</code> argument.</p>

<h3>As percent</h3>

<p>Another technique is to compare the percentage growth since last week.
Let's imagine we are looking at sales or signup numbers.
We could graph today's sales per minute vs those from last week.</p>

<p>To do that, Graphite has the <code>asPercent</code> function. This function
takes a series representing <em>100%</em> and second to compare against.
The function call looks a bit scary so let me try to break it down over
multiple lines:</p>

<p><code>
asPercent(
  summarize(sumSeries(stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.accounts.response_time.count),"1min")
  ,timeShift(summarize(sumSeries(stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.accounts.response_time.count), "1min"),"1w")
)
</code></p>

<p>The first argument is the summarized RPMs (requests per minute) and the
second is last week's summarized RPMs.</p>

<p>Here is how the graph looks:</p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite/graphite-compare-as-percent.png" alt="graphite as percent" /></p>

<p>Based on all the data we collect, we can now graph something like that:</p>

<p><img src="/images/graphite/graphite-as-percent.png" alt="graphite as percent with multiple series" /></p>

<p>This graph is basically the same as the one above, but we used the
overall response time as the 100% value and we graphed all the different
monitored sections of our code base.</p>

<p>You can now build some really advanced tools that look at trends,
check pre- and post-deployment measurements, trigger alerts, and help you refactor your
code.</p>

<p>Maybe you suspect that your app has a chokepoint at the database level.
You can track the query types and the targeted tables per API
endpoint. You can see where you spend most of the time and which code path
is responsible for it. You can quickly see if adding indicies or other database-level techniques actually make a difference.</p>

<h2>Other tips</h2>

<h3>Share a url into campfire/irc and see a preview</h3>

<p>Campfire and many other chat tools offer image preview as long as they
detect that the url has an image extension. Unfortunately, Graphite's
graph urls look more like this:</p>

<p><code>
http://graphite.awesome.graphs.com/render?width=400&amp;from=-4hours&amp;until=-&amp;height=400&amp;target=summarize(sumSeries(stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.accounts.response_time.count))&amp;drawNullAsZero=true&amp;title=Example&amp;_uniq=0.11944825737737119
</code></p>

<p>To get a preview, just append the with: <code>&amp;.jpg</code></p>

<h3>Get the graph data in JSON format</h3>

<p>You might want to do something fancy with the data like
create alerts. For that you can ask Graphite for a json representation
of the data by adding <code>&amp;format=json</code> to the URL.</p>

<p>```json
[
 {"target":
  "summarize(sumSeries(stats.timers.accounts.*.http.post.accounts.response_time.count))",
  "datapoints": [</p>

<pre><code>[20260.0, 137256960],[19513, 1372357020] //[...]
</code></pre>

<p>   ]
  }
]
```</p>

<p>The data points are the timestamped value of each graphed point.
Note that you can also ask for the CSV version of the data then pass it on to some poor bastard using Excel.</p>

<h3>Only show top graphs</h3>

<p>Let say that you are graphing the response time of all your APIs. The
amount of displayed graphs can be overwhelming.</p>

<p>To limit the displayed graphs, use one of the filters. For instance the <code>currentAbove</code> or
<code>averageAbove</code> filters that can help you only display web services with
more than X RPMs for instance. Using filters can be very useful to find
outliers.</p>

<h2>Get going with Graphite!</h2>

<p>Hopefully this guide will help and inspire you to start using Graphite to easily collect and analyze your metrics.
I'm sure there are great tricks I forgot to mention, please add your favorites in the comments.</p>

<p><em>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/j3">Jeff Casimir</a> for reviewing this post
before its publication!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
